1969年3月至2003年10月 人类曾有一段超音速民航旅行史
From March 1969 until October 2003, we had supersonic passenger travel.
搭乘协和式飞机 只需三小时我们就能从纽约飞到伦敦
With Concorde, we could travel from New York to London in just 3 hours,
在之前至少要7小时
a journey that would previously take at least 7 hours.
人类只花了十多年 就让长途飞行发生了翻天覆地的变化
In just over a decade, long haul flights had changed dramatically.
民航越来越安全
Airplanes were crashing less,
机票越来越便宜
flights were getting cheaper
人们也有了越来越多看看大千世界的机会
and the world was opening up to more and more people.
每天都有新航线开辟出来
With new routes appearing every day,
人们甚至可以去那些听都没听说过的国家
people were able to visit countries they probably didn't even know existed.
在那个飞行的黄金年代里
During this golden age of flying,
飞机在人们眼中一直是种既舒适又有魅力的旅行方式
airplanes were seen as a more comfortable and glamorous way to travel.
快进到今天 民航变得更加安全、高效、价格低廉
Fast forward to now, and airplanes are much safer, efficient and cheaper.
但纽约到伦敦的速度却比协和出现之前还要慢了
But that New York to London flight time is now slower than it was prior to Concorde's arrival.
民航发展50年 怎么还越飞越慢了？
After 50 years of aircraft development, how can we have gotten slower?
未来航天技术的发展 能为民航带来当年协和那样的跨越吗？
And could the future of spaceflight give us the next big leap in technology just like Concorde did?
想要回答这个问题 我们首先要知道协和为什么会失败——
To answer this, we need to know why Concorde failed in the first place -
以及飞机为什么不一定越快越好
and why faster airplanes aren't necessarily better.
原因很简单：钱
The simple answer is money.
当然实际情况要复杂亿点点
But it's a little more complex than that.
飞机的燃油效率多年来已经大有提升
The fuel efficiency of airplanes has gotten much better over time.
这主要源于人类对提高燃油效率的需求
This is largely down to the demand for increased efficiency,
而这个需求在2000年代达到了历史最高水平
which reached an all-time high in the 2000's,
当时航空燃油价格从每加仑70美分飙升到3美元
when the price of jet fuel rose from 70 cents per gallon to 3 dollars.
因此工程师必须为现代飞机寻求提升燃油效率的新方法
So engineers had to look for new ways to increase the fuel efficiency of modern airplanes.
他们发现增大发动机的体积就能大大提高燃油效率
They found that by increasing the size of the engines, it could drastically change their efficiency.
因为空气在航空发动机中有两条流动路线
This is because the air can take two different paths through a jet engine.
一部分走内涵道
Some of the air passes through the center,
这条路线途径几级压气机 然后与燃油混合并点燃
where it goes through a series of compressors before it gets ignited by the jet fuel.
产生额外推力 并驱动风扇转动
This creates additional thrust and also powers the fan.
其余的空气则会流经外涵道的风扇 直接抛向后方
The rest of the air simply bypasses this section and is thrown out the back,
同样也会产生大量推力
also creating a large amount of thrust.
在过去 发动机主要推力来自内涵道
In the past, engines would typically get most of their thrust from the jet section.
但工程师发现只要增大风扇体积 让更多空气走外涵道
But engineers found that by increasing the fan size and bypassing more air,
发动机就能用更少的燃料提供更大的推力 从而提升燃油效率
the engines could produce more thrust with less fuel, therefore increasing the efficiency.
相反的例子就是协和 它用的涡轮喷气发动机中几乎所有推力都来自内涵道
In contrast, Concorde used turbojet engines which got almost all of their thrust from burning fuel,
导致效率远低于现代发动机
making them much less efficient than modern day engines.
其他飞机制造商都在大搞节能减排
As aircraft manufacturers continue to lower their emissions,
协和这大排量显然不受各大航司待见
it's clear that Concorde's fuel guzzling image wouldn't be very popular today.
Starship的长途飞行大约会产生700吨的二氧化碳
A long haul Starship flight would produce around 700 tonnes of CO2,
平均每位乘客0.8吨
this works out at around 0.8 tonnes per passenger.
波音747的数值与它很接近 甚至还要低一点
Compare this to a 747 and the amount per passenger is very similar, if not a little bit less.
协和每次飞行的二氧化碳排放量是六倍左右
Concorde's CO2 output would be around 6 times more than this per flight.
多亏了这些新款高效的航空发动机
Thanks to these newer and more efficient engines,
让现代民航客机的排量跟协和比简直是天壤之别
modern airplanes really separated themselves from Concorde in terms of their emissions.
但这些新的大型发动机有一个弱点 并最终影响了飞行时间
But these new larger engines had one weakness that ended up affecting flight times.
如果太多的空气通过这些较大的发动机 风扇基本上会像一堵墙一样
If too much air passed through these larger engines, the fan would basically act like a wall,
拖慢飞机速度 从而需要燃烧更多燃料
slowing the plane down and requiring more jet fuel to be burned.
这就是为什么飞机制造商都会推荐一个最佳的巡航速度
This is why aircraft manufacturers recommend an optimal cruising speed
这个速度在880-925公里每小时之间
between 880 and 925km/h,
此时发动机效率最高
where the engines are most efficient.
什么概念呢？60年代的一个民航客机速度就已接近1000公里每小时了
To put that into perspective, a typical passenger jet in the 60's
would fly much closer to 1,000km/h.
以稍慢的速度飞行为航司节省了很多钱
Flying at these slower speeds saves airlines an enormous amount of money.
捷蓝航空一年靠每趟飞行平均多飞两分钟就节省了1350万美元
JetBlue saved 13 and a half million dollars in a single year
by simply adding 2 minutes to their flight times.
随着新一代的飞机越来越注重燃油效率与成本节约
With newer airplanes being much more focused on efficiency and cost saving,
协和的运营成本逐渐开始离谱了起来
Concorde's extreme running cost started to seem more and more absurd.
Starship的运营成本毫无疑问也会很高
The running costs for Starship will no doubt be high as well,
但有一个区别是 Starship可以运送更多乘客
but one of the differences is that Starship will be able to carry many more passengers -
大约是协和的8倍
around 8 times more than Concorde.
预计每次地球点对点飞行成本为100万美元
With an estimated running cost of just over 1 million dollars per Earth flight,
平均下来票价1200美元
that puts the average ticket price at around 1,200 dollars.
与协和的票价相比 这已经是一个重大的改进了
This is a major improvement over Concorde's ticket prices
还能为更多的人开辟了一种新的旅行方式 这是协和无法做到的
and opens up a new way of travelling to more people than Concorde ever could.
但即使有这样的票价
But even with these ticket prices,
也很难看出Starship如何能取代传统民航飞机
it's difficult to see how Starship could take over traditional airplanes.
今天的乘客不太可能为更快的飞行支付更多费用
A passenger today is much less likely to pay more for a quicker flight.
我们现在有能力在世界任何地方进行商务会议
We now have the ability to conduct business meetings from anywhere in the world
整段飞行旅程有个手机也差不多够了
and all the inflight entertainment we need on our phones.
这在协和那年代是完全没法比的
None of this was possible when Concorde was around.
尽管如此 如果票价能与商务舱票价相当 Starship仍可能是首选的交通方式
Despite this, Starship might be a preferred transport method
if the ticket price can match that of a business class ticket.
任何飞机或火箭的目标都是最终付清其购买成本并实现收支平衡
The goal for any aircraft or rocket is to eventually pay off its purchase cost and break-even.
对于一架民航飞机 通常在购买后的5到10年左右就能回本
For a typical aircraft, this usually happens around 5 to 10 years after it was purchased.
在这一时间点之后 飞机还能运营多年并继续盈利
Airplanes are expected to operate many years after this point and continue making a profit.
但是对于一架飞机来说 不能只看重它的机龄
But for an airplane, it's not just the number of years that contribute towards its age,
还要注意它经历的压力循环次数
but how many pressure cycles it has gone through.
飞机每次起飞
Every time an aircraft takes off,
客舱都会为了能让乘客在高空正常呼吸而进行加压
its cabin needs to be pressurized to make sure that everyone can breathe at high altitudes.
这个加压过程会对飞机的机身和机翼产生相当大的压力
This pressurization puts a considerable amount of stress on the airplane's fuselage and wings.
随着时间的推移 这种压力会导致飞机出现裂缝
Over time, this stress causes cracks to appear in the airplane,
并最终影响安全飞行
which will eventually become too dangerous to fly.
一旦飞机达到了最大的循环次数
Once the airplane has reached its maximum number of cycles,
就必须被报废或进行成本高昂的维修
it has to be either scrapped or put through a costly amount of maintenance.
原文注：空客A380平均寿命约27年
一架空客A380在退役前可以飞行35000次
An Airbus A380, can make about 35,000 flights before being retired.
而协和的次数更少
Concorde was flown much less frequently,
平均飞行次数只有约5000
with an average number of flights at around 5,000.
同样的事情也会发生在火箭上
The same ageing process happens with rockets.
Starship的重要特点就是可以飞行上百次而不需要任何翻修
Starship is meant to be capable of hundreds of flights before any refurbishment is needed,
但从现实来看 还没有人知道它到底能飞多少个循环
but realistically, no one knows exactly how many cycles it will be capable of.
尽管它不太可能达到飞机的飞行次数
Although it's unlikely to reach an airplane's number of flights,
但Starship还有一个相比于协和或其它飞机的独特优势
it does have one advantage that sets it apart from Concorde or typical airplanes.
每架协和的造价大约为两亿美元
The production cost for each Concorde was around 200 million dollars.
而当Starship完全投入运营的时候
Once Starship is fully operational,
全尺寸Starship的造价可以低至四千万美元
the cost for a full Starship stack could be as low as 40 million dollars.
因为从各方面来讲 火箭的制造其实都比飞机要简单
This is because in many ways, rockets are more simple to manufacture than airplanes.
火箭大部分都是燃料罐 钱主要花在了发动机上
The majority of the rocket is just a giant fuel tank with the engines taking up most of the cost.
如果太空叉能达到Starship的成本目标
If SpaceX can reach its cost target for Starship,
那么它有可能比运营协和更早回本
then it might be capable of breaking-even much sooner than Concorde ever could.
在许多方面 Starship似乎都有潜力去避开协和踩过的坑
In many ways, it seems like Starship could potentially get around the pitfalls that ended Concorde.
而尽管火箭取代客机的想法目前还只是一个梦想
And although the idea of rockets replacing airliners is currently just a dream,
重要的是要记住 曾经有人对飞机说过同样的话
it's important to remember that the same thing was once said about airplanes.
20世纪早期的飞机长这德行
In the early 20th century, the only airplanes that existed looked like this
都是一帮满腔热血的疯子工程师造的
and they were being built by crazy and ambitious engineers.
而等资本加入后 技术就开始极速发展
As soon as money got involved, the technology started to develop extremely quickly.
发动机越来越先进 飞机也造得越来越大
Engines became more advanced and the planes themselves started to grow larger and larger,
能拉越来越多的人和货
allowing them to carry more people and more cargo.
快进到现在 显然很多事情大有改善
Fast forward to now and it's easy to see how much things have improved.
民航飞机是最安全的交通工具之一
Air travel is now one of the safest forms of transport
一架飞机可以载着850名乘客飞行14000多公里
and airplanes are capable of flying 9,000 miles whilst carrying 850 passengers at a time.
人类真的很牛逼
We really have come a long way!
因此 尽管目前还不清楚Starship是否会彻底改变我们在地球上的旅行方式
So although it's unclear whether Starship will revolutionize how we travel around Earth,
但生在一个能见证如此多历史被创造的时代 是一件何其有幸的事情
it's incredible to be alive at a time when so much history is being made.
如果您想支持本频道 欢迎考虑去Patreon赞助
If you'd like to support the channel even more, consider becoming a Patron
从而把您的名字加入视频结尾 并能进入独家Discord群
where you can give your input on each video and get exclusive access to our Discord server.
非常感谢您的观看 我们下期视频再见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.